Inventory of the James A. Bill Papers 1940-2003
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
James A. Bill Papers 1940-2003
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2003.66
36.00
Series 1 contains research information for the Eagle and the Lion, Series 2 contains Book and Article Reviews for works by James Bill (other than Eagle and the Lion), Series 3 contains information on the Iran Contra Affair, Series 4 contains the Collection of Interview Transcripts and Notes, letters and miscellaneous materials (concerning George Ball and Henry Kissinger), Series 5 contains mostly journals, newsletters and brochures concerning Iran and the Middle East, written by James Bill, Series 6 contains miscellaneous materials and documents concerning the Schuman Plan [book by George Ball] and Bilderberg conferences attended by George Ball, Series 7 contains mostly documents, memorandums and letters concerning Bilderberg Meetings from 1956 to 1988, Series 8 contains three books about modern Iran and industry and development, series 9 contains books concerning the statistical surveys and census of Iran, Series 10 contains books authored and co-authored by James A bill, Series 11 contains video tapes concerning Iran, Islam and the Middle East, Series 12 contains dissertations and theses supervised and dedicated to James A. Bill, and Series 13 contains cassette tapes concerning interviews conducted by James A. Bill.
Bill, James A. arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center from James A. Bill on 11/24/2003.
Biographical Note
James A. Bill received his B.A. at Assumption College and his M.A. from Penn State University in 1965. He received his doctorate from Princeton University in 1968 and went on to teach at the University of Texas in 1968. He taught comparative politics and specialized in Middle Eastern Studies. He has also written a number of articles, journals and five books. He joined the Government Department at the College of William and Mary in 1987. He also became the director of the Wendy and Emery Reves Center for International Studies. He retired from the Reves Center in 1998 and continued to teach until 2004. He has written a number of books, most notably The Eagle and the Lion (Yale) a study on Iran-U.S. relations. His book Behind the Scenes in U.S. Foreign Policy (Yale) is also noteworthy.
Scope and Contents
Series 1 contains research information for the Eagle and the Lion, Series 2 contains Book and Article Reviews for works by James Bill (other than Eagle and the Lion), Series 3 contains information on the Iran Contra Affair, Series 4 contains the Collection of Interview Transcripts and Notes, letters and miscellaneous materials (concerning George Ball and Henry Kissinger), Series 5 contains mostly journals, newsletters and brochures concerning Iran and the Middle East, written by James Bill, Series 6 contains miscellaneous materials and documents concerning the Schuman Plan [book by George Ball] and Bilderberg conferences attended by George Ball, Series 7 contains mostly documents, memorandums and letters concerning Bilderberg Meetings from 1956 to 1988, Series 8 contains three books about modern Iran and industry and development, series 9 contains books concerning the statistical surveys and census of Iran, Series 10 contains books authored and co-authored by James A bill, Series 11 contains video tapes concerning Iran, Islam and the Middle East, Series 12 contains dissertations and theses supervised and dedicated to James A. Bill, and Series 13 contains cassette tapes concerning interviews conducted by James A. Bill.
Arrangement of Materials
This collection remains predominantly in its original order. The information is divided by series titled in the original order filed by Prof. Bill. The major sub groups were also put into acid free folders and titled by their original folders. Those folders without titles were organized within the inventory by the context of the information provided.
Additional Information
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
College of William and Mary--Reves Center--20th Century
Family Name:
Ball family.; Pahlavi family
Genre/Form of Material:
Clippings; Correspondence; Manuscripts (document genre)
Geographic Name:
Iran--1940s; Iran--1950s
Personal Name:
Ball, George W.(Wildman), 1909-1994; Kissinger, Henry A. (Alfred), 1923-; Mohammad Reza Shah Pahlavi, 1919-1980; Mossadegh, Mohammed, 1882-1967
Topical Term:
United States--Kennedy Administration--Iran--Foreign Policy; United States--Lyndon B. Johnson--Iran--Foreign Policy; United States--Truman Administration--Iran--Foreign Policy
Detailed Description of the Collection
  Series 1: The Eagle and the Lion Research
- The Eagle and the Lion Research, 1941-1986, bulk 1951-1979
  Box 1 contains documents and files concerning the chapters 1-2 of The Eagle and the Lion; Iran in the 1940s, papers and files concerning T. Cuyler Young, information on Iran and America from the 1940-1950s; Azerbaijan Issue/President Truman's Ultimatum Question; Americans in Iran; and US Policy toward Iran in 1940s.
  Box 2 contains notes, papers, newspaper articles, telegrams, correspondences concerning chapter 3-4 of the eagle and the lion and Iran from 1953-1960; Mussadiq period; Transcript of the End of Empire Documentary; photocopied documents and transcripts concerning National Archives, 1951; Oil industry issue in Iran; Church Hearings; Mussadiq and the coup of 1953; Reviews on Counter Coup written by Kermit Roosevelt; Communist Threat; Correspondences concerning James Bill, Ronald Ferrier, Ian Beer, Dan Wilber, Mark Gasiorowski; John C. Campbell, Professor T. Cuyler Young; Kennedy Administration, 1961-1963; Iran in the news; Department of State Records; handwritten and typed notes on Iran; Journal Articles/Excerpts from Books on Iran; Khrushchev, Kennedy and Iran; Hassan Arsanjani; two letters from T. Cuyler Young to WW Rostow could not be located; Box 3 contains documents, newspapers, letters, pamphlets and magazine articles from 1970-1977;typed and handwritten notes on Chapter 5-6; Lindon B. Johnson Administration, 1963-1967; Cuyler Young correspondences and papers; Iran in Newspapers, Journals, and other publications, Development and Reform in Iran; US Arms Sales to Iran, Kayhan International newspaper; Henry Kissinger, Armin H. Meyer; documents in Farsi; The Shah's Visits to US; US/Iran Military Connections and US Arms Sales; Amir Abbas Hoveyda, Intellectuals; Box 4 contains information for Chapter 7; sources and documents concerning various forms of Energy; Oil/National Iranian Oil Company [NIOC]; Bill Butler; Arms Sales to Iran/Iran's Foreign Policy; Newspapers Iran 1975-1976; Iran's foreign policy, US/Golf war considerations; Sadegh Ghotbzadeh; Carter Administration; Ibrahim Yazdi; General Robert E. Huyser; Black Friday
  Box 5 contains resources for Chapter 9 of Eagle and the Lion; Iranian Western politics; Kissinger and the Rockefellers; Joseph Kraft; Congressional Record Materials: chronologically 1979; Communist threat; hostage situation; Iran in the news; other material for chapter 9; Box 6 includes resources for chapter 10 of Eagle and the Lion; US Embassy interview schedule; British Embassy; Commissary; US Consulate; Invitation Lists for by James Bill; American School in Tehran; IAS [Iran-America Society] - RPIP [Regional Public Improvement Project] - USIS [United States Information Service] (Survey); Murray Smith[?];Notes, Correspondence, Interview Notes for Chapter 10; Booklets; other material concerning chapter 10.
    Subseries 1: Chapter 1 of The Eagle and the Lion
  - Chapter 1 of The Eagle and the Lion (1)
    - (1)
        Subseries 1: T. Cuyler Young Files and Papers
      - T. Cuyler Young Files and Papers (1)
        - Articles on the Tudeh party by Iranians + notes on Shinpartus Dr. Tagi [Taqi?] Erani in a Life of Service. A Novel (Tehran: Tudeh-yi-Iran, 1944) (1)
        - Press Translation Service Alborz College of Teheran- brief summaries of news articles in Iranian press. (1, 2)
        - Bibliography (pages are stuck together): International Index and Donaldson Studies in Muslim Ethics. (1, 3)
        - Report #261; Mobayan Les elections; Eskandari; Arzu; and Timeline of government events in Iran 1306-1320 [1927-1937] - including lists of Majlis, laws passed, issues [mainly internal, some foreign], debates, reforms, problems that Iran is facing, etc. These descriptions of government issues and events are accompanied by Journal de Teheran and Ettelaat articles (1, 4)
        - History of Political Events in Iran from September 16, 1941- March 9, 1942. (1, 5)
        Subseries 2: Azerbaijan Issue/ President Truman's Ultimatum Question
      - Azerbaijan Issue/ President Truman's Ultimatum Question (1, 2)
        - (1, 2, 6)
          - Evolution of Cold War- From Policy to Commitment- excerpt from unspecified book. (1, 2, 6)
          - Truman Ultimatum to Stalin and the 1946 Azerbaijan Crisis: Fact or Fantasy?: article by James A. Thorpe **stuck together** [in the Society for Iranian Studies Newsletter 4], October 1972 (1, 2, 6)
          - A Peripheral View of the Origins of the Cold War: The Crises in Iran, 1941-47: article by Stephen L. McFarland in Diplomatic History v.4, n.4, Fall 1980 (1, 2, 6)
          - Notes on parts of K. Tabari dissertation: subjects- Oil in 1940s, Azerbaijan Crisis and Iran 1940s, and Iran 1940s. (1, 2, 6)
          - Truman Ultimatum to Stalin and the 1946 Azerbaijan Crisis: The Making of a Myth: article by James A. Thorpe in Journal of Politics v. 40, 1978 (1, 2, 6)
          - Memorandum by Edwin M. Wright to Herbert Fine 8/16/65: Wright personal account of the events as he experienced/remembers them. (1, 2, 6)
          - The Cheshire Ultimatum: Truman Message to Stalin in the 1946 Azerbaijan Crisis: article by J. Phillip Rosenberg in Journal of Politics 40 (February 1978). (1, 2, 6)
          - United Nations Action: The Iranian Case 1946: small book by Richard W. Van Wagenen (Carnegie Endowment for the International Peace). (1, 2, 6)
        Subseries 3: Americans in Iran.
      - Americans in Iran. (1, 3)
        - (1, 3, 7)
          - Lines of Personal and Organizational Conflict: flowchart. (1, 3, 7)
          - Special Envoy to Churchill and Stalin 1941-1946: book by W. Averell Harriman and Elie Abel (New York: Random House, 1975). (1, 3, 7)
          - Handwritten Flowchart of Americans connected with Iran. (1, 3, 7)
          - "American Advisers in Persia: article by George V. Allen in Department of State Bulletin July 23, 1944 v.XI, n. 265 (1, 3, 7)
          - Excerpts from Americans in Persia by Arthur C. Millspaugh (Washington, DC: The Brookings Institution, 1946). (1, 3, 7)
          - "Iran in Wartime": article by John N. Greely, Brigadier General, US Army in National Geographic v. LXXXIV, n. 2 August, 1943. (1, 3, 7)
          - Notes on T. H. Vail Motter book United States Army in World War II- The Middle Eastern Theatre: The Persian Corridor and Aid to Russia (Washington, DC: Department of the Army, 1952) [I have presumed that this is the book from which these notes came because it is in Lion and Eagle bibliography and the notes taken make sense that it would be from this book]. (1, 3, 7)
        Subseries 4: US Policy toward Iran in 1940s
      - US Policy toward Iran in 1940s (1, 4)
        - (1, 4, 8)
          - Excerpts from James F. Schnabel The History of the Joint Chiefs of Staff vol. 1 1945-1947 (Wilmington, DE: Michael Glazier, 1979). (1, 4, 8)
          - Excerpts from Kenneth W. Condit The History of the Joint Chiefs of Staff vol. 2 1947-1949 (Wilmington, DE: Michael Glazier, 1979). (1, 4, 8)
          - Containment in Iran, 1946: The Shift to Active Policy: article by Richard Pfau in Diplomatic History v.1, n.4 Fall 1977. (1, 4, 8)
          - Notes on Bruce R. Kuniholm book The Origins of the Cold War in the Near East (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1980). (1, 4, 8)
          - - Notes on Documents Book: Y. Alexander: [Possibly from Alexander, Yonah and Allan Nanes, Eds. The United States and Iran (Frederick, MD: Aletheia Books, 1980) This book is in The Lion and the Eagle bibliography]. (1, 4, 8)
          - Excerpt from Thomas A. Bryson book Seeds of Mideast Crisis: The United States Diplomatic Role in the Middle East During World War II (Jefferson, NC: McFarland and Co., 1981). (1, 4, 8)
          - US Military Missions to Iran, 1943-1978: The Political Economy of Military Assistance: article by Thomas M. Ricks in Iranian Studies v. XII, n.3-4 Summer-Autumn 1979. (1, 4, 8)
          - Notes on the Constitutional Revolution [in Iran] 1905-6 [Probably from A History of the Iran- American Relations by Rahim Rezazadeh Malek. (1, 4, 8)
          - Poem from A History of the Iran- American Relations by Rahim Rezazadeh Malek. (1, 4, 8)
        Subseries 5: Other Notes Regarding Iran in the 1940s
      - Other Notes Regarding Iran in the 1940s (1, 5)
        - (1, 5, 9)
          - Notes on the Shah visit to US in 1949. (1, 5, 9)
          - Letter from Ernie [Earnest R. Ivey] to Jim [James Bill], 1/27/1985 (1, 5, 9)
          - Notes from interview with George Lenczowski in San Francisco, 11/30/1984 (1, 5, 9)
          - Handwritten revisions in 1940s Chapter. (1, 5, 9)
          - Notes from Iranian publications on: some of Mussadeq speeches (translations); book about Qavam; Mussadiq reaction to Millspaugh; collection of articles by Dr. Fatemi. (1, 5, 9)
    Subseries 2: Mussadiq Period- Chapter 2 of The Eagle and the Lion- Plus Other 1940s-50s
  - Mussadiq Period- Chapter 2 of The Eagle and the Lion- Plus Other 1940s-50s (2)
    - (2, 1)
        Subseries 1: Transcript of the End of Empire Documentary
      - Transcript of the End of Empire Documentary (2, 1)
        - (2, 1, 10)
          - Interview with Professor Richard Cottam: American professor of Iranian studies. (2, 1, 10)
          - Interview with Colonel Stephen Meade: sent to keep Shah in power by Eisenhower; helped convince Princess Ashraf to get Shah to support coup. (2, 1, 10)
          - Interview with Walter Levy: American oil expert who served in Iran as negotiator between Mussadiq and AIOC concerning nationalization. (2, 1, 10)
          - Interview with Julian Amery: British, does not believe Iran had legal right to nationalize. (2, 1, 10)
        - (2, 1, 11)
          - Interview with Averill Harriman: American sent to Iran to aid in negotiations between Mussadiq and Great Britain. (2, 1, 11)
          - Interview with Henry Byroade: Assistant Secretary of State for Eisenhower. (2, 1, 11)
          - Interview with Sam Falle: British, at first was sympathetic to Mussadiq nationalization movement. (2, 1, 11)
          - Interview with [Shapour] Bakhtiar: liberal Iranian, member of National Front. (2, 1, 11)
        - (2, 1, 12)
          - Interview with Sir Peter Ramsbottom: British, part of Stokes mission. (2, 1, 12)
          - Interview with George McGhee: Assistant Secretary of State for Truman. (2, 1, 12)
          - Interview with [?] Rouhani: defends Mussadiq. (2, 1, 12)
          - Interview with Peter Avery: talented Iranologist [British?]who came to Abadan as a teacher (2, 1, 12)
        Subseries 2: National Archives- 1951: Photocopied documents
      - National Archives- 1951: Photocopied documents (2, 1)
        - (2, 1, 13)
          - The Present State of the Iranian Nation: memo from J. J. Wagner to A. L. Richards 1/11/51: discusses Razmara and the Communist threat in Iran (2, 1, 13)
          - TEHRAN 539 memorandum of The Present State of the Iranian Nation: summary of above memo and concludes that Shah is keystone to Iran government, 1/18/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - From state dept. to Am. Embassy in Tehran: on Time article that offended the Shah, 2/3/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - From Tehran to the Sec. of State (Acheson): on the Time article and Shah reaction, 2/7/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - From Tehran to Sec. of State: Time article mostly bad-mouthed Princess Ashraf- US official refuses to apologize for American journalists, 2/9/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - Letter from Joseph J. Wagner to C. Vaughn Ferguson, Jr. (Tehran to Washington): Ashraf unhappy about brother marriage; Crown lands have been sold; Razmara still in power but ineffective, 2/15/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - Foreign Service Dispatch [sic] from Tehran to Dept. of State: Princess Fatemeh Pahlavi and her husband are leaving Iran and coming to California, 6/6/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - Letter from E. J. Joosten to President Truman: Joosten wanted to know if it was true that the US was sending soldiers to help Iran start army, 6/20/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - Letter, reply to Joosten from Grace B. Ruckh (Information Officer, Division of Public Liaison: some military assistance has been sent (2, 1, 13)
          - Department of State- telegram from Tehran to Sec. of State: Ashraf and family go to Switzerland; suspected for political reasons, 9/23/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - Foreign Service Dispatch from Am. Embassy in Tehran to Dept. of State: Shah speech to Majlis, 9/25/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - Assessment of Political Situation Iran: Mussadiq rule; failure of Great Britain; Communist threat in Iran, 10/05/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - Telegram from Loy Henderson to SECSTATE: Henderson is American Ambassador to Iran; a summary view of the forces in Iran at this time: who is who, who is strong, who is weak, who is a part or at least susceptible to communist threat, 10/22/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - - Telegram from Henderson to SECSTATE: On October 30, 1951 high school and University of Tehran students held an organized demonstration in solidarity with Egyptian students to protest GB moves in Egypt, 10/30/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - - Memorandum of Conversation btw Dr. Ahmad Human, Deputy Minister of Court and Mr. John H. Stutesman, Second Secretary: Dr. Human take on the situation on Iran including the communist threat, Mussadiq- personal qualities and abilities, 11/6/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - Telegram from Loy Henderson to SECSTATE Summary of conversation between Kashani and A L Richards, 11/12/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - - Memorandum of Conversation btw Dr. Ahmad Human and John H. Stutesman: Dr. Human believes that a communist coup detat was possible, 11/27/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - - Telegram from Loy Henderson to SECSTATE WASH: This describes a conversation between Henderson and Jemal Emami, Majlis Opposition leader, 12/4/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - Telegram from Loy Henderson to SECSTATE WASH: Henderson ate dinner with Ala, MinCourt [Hussein Ala, Minister to the Court?], 12/12/1951 (2, 1, 13)
          - Memorandum of Conversation: Mr. Shahbaz and Mohsen Pezeshpur: Pezeshpur is the leader of the Pan-Iranist Party. He is anti-communist (describes USSR as territorial aggressor), anti-British (describes GB as political aggressor), and anti-US (describes US as economic aggressor)., 12/20/1951 (2, 1, 13)
        Subseries 3: Oil
      - Oil (2, 1, 3)
        - (2, 1, 3, 14)
          - Memorandum of Conversation- Department of State Iranian Oil Problem: Acheson and George McGhee discuss the complexity of the oil issue in Iran with relation to US with Presidents and CEOs of top American oil companies, 10/10/1951 (2, 1, 3, 14)
          - Memorandum of Secretary Conversation with President: Acheson proposes that US support GB resolution and push Mussadiq for a 50/50 split, 10/10/1951 (2, 1, 3, 14)
          - Memorandum of Conversation: Dept. of State: discussion of Iran oil crisis; GB decision to gradually withdraw technicians from Iran; the International Court findings in case between Iran and GB, 7/11/1951 (2, 1, 3, 14)
          - Memorandum from US Department of the Interior Petroleum Administration for Defense Iranian Oil Problem: Charles Rayner suggestions to solve Iranian oil problem with assumption that Iran does have right to nationalize, 10/22/1951 (2, 1, 3, 14)
          - National Intelligence Estimate: The Importance of Iranian and Middle East Oil to Western Europe Under Peacetime Conditions: concludes that West needs Middle East oil- without it there would be major rationing; Iran is necessary but could be lived without (2, 1, 3, 14)
          - Department of State Telegram: GB is broke and cannot give up AIOC at present time; GB believes US should support her- rather see Iran go Communist than GB go bankrupt, 11/10/1951 (2, 1, 3, 14)
          - Some Documents on the Nationalization of the Oil Industry in Iran- Iranian Embassy Washington, DC: text of laws that nationalized and regulated oil industry; grievances of Iran against AIOC [another copy of this is in A Report of the History of the Southern Oil of Iran...]; text of Mussadiq report to Majlis on official recognition of nationalization by GB and AIOC; reply of Head of Iranian delegation to statement made by Harriman on AIOC controversy; letter from Mussadiq to Harriman, 3/20/1951 (2, 1, 3, 14)
          - The Text of the Prime Minister Reports to the Majlis on the Developments of Saheb-Gharanieh Oil Conference Submitted at the Session of 30th Mordad, 1330: details the Stokes mission: negotiations between Iran and GB with help of Harriman, 8/22/1951 (2, 1, 3, 14)
          - A Report of the History of the Southern Oil of Iran presented by the National Oil Company of Iran to the Hon. Averell Harriman, special envoy of the President of USA: grievances Iran has with AIOC since DArcy concession [same as in Some Documents on Nationalization of Oil Industry...], 8/1/1951 (2, 1, 3, 14)
          - Text of the Report Submitted by Mussadiq on 11/25/51 Upon Return from US and Egypt 1/4/52 [there are 2 copies of this]: Mussadiq goes to New York to plead Iran case in front of UN Security Council against GB accusations: concerning nationalization of oil, does Iran have right to do it? (2, 1, 3, 14)
          - American Foreign Policy 1950-1955 Basic Documents Vol. II- Department of State December 1957: Section on Iranian Oil Controversy- US role in controversy and info. on Consortium (2, 1, 3, 14)
          - Text of Report Submitted by Mussadiq to Majless re: British Technical Staff and Speech to the People in Baharestan Square, 9/27/1951 (2, 1, 3, 14)
          - Discour de M. Le Docteur Mossadegh sur la Nationalisation du Pétrole en Iran (The Speech of H. E. Dr. Mossadeq? concerning the Nationalization of Petroleum Industry in Iran) 1951: grievances of AIOC (2, 1, 3, 14)
        - (2, 1, 3, 15)
          - Minutes of Meeting Held at White House Iranian Oil: discussion of next move in oil crisis of GB, US and Iran govts.; how much US and GB should buy Iran oil for; should Truman and Churchill jointly sign a message to Mussadiq, 8/21/1952 (2, 1, 3, 15)
          - Prime Minister Reports Tehran: documents concerning the International Court case tried in Hague: GB claimed that Iran nationalization of oil was unfair and would threaten world peace, 10/1952 (2, 1, 3, 15)
          - The Speech Delivered by Dr. Mohammad Mossadeq, the Prime Minister at Meeting of the Deputies of the 17th Majlis: discusses economic trouble that Iran is in because GB is not buying its oil, 4/12/1952 (2, 1, 3, 15)
          - Speech Delivered by Mussadiq at Gathering of American Press: airs grievances with GB about oil and thanks US for support, 3/18/1952 (2, 1, 3, 15)
          - Memorandum of Conversation- Department of State 10/8/52: Discusses problems between Mussadiq and GB; US needs on proposal of way for Mussadiq to get financial assistance quickly (2, 1, 3, 15)
        - (2, 1, 3, 16)